MISSION 26 "IT'S JUST OBON."
（任务26 盂兰盆节）
Is everyone ready to go?
大家都准备好了吗？
Let's go!
那就出发吧！
It's hot again today. It's supposed to get up to 35 degrees!
今天也好热 听说最高气温有35度
Was summer always this hot?
以前夏天有这么热吗？
Compared to ten years ago.
与十年前相比的话
And then Ms. Aoyama from next door said,
于是隔壁的青山太太就说了
"That's no way to raise children."
“这样对小孩的教育不好”
And everyone got mad.
结果把大家刺激到了
The coating is crisp and thin,
那种鲷鱼烧的外皮很薄
and the sweet filling goes all the way to the tail.
连尾巴的部分都塞满了馅
But I think…
可是我啊…
Oh, anyone want a salt candy?
对了 要不要吃盐糖？
We have to be careful of heatstroke.
得预防中暑才行
Komi family, business as usual.
一如既往的古见一家
When a person has extreme social anxiety,
所谓的“交流障碍症” 是指不擅长和人交流的一种症状
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有这种症状的人
Bear in mind,
不过需要注意的是
they only struggle to form connections.
这些人只是不擅长社交
It doesn't mean that they don't want to.
但并不表示他们不想和别人有往来
You had a nice, long chat.
看你聊了很久呢
Did you properly greet your ancestors?
好好问候过祖先了吗？
NOD
（点头）
It's been ages, Mom.
好久不见 妈
KOMI'S GRANDMOTHER: YUIKO KOMI
（古见同学的祖母 古见结子）
Come in.
进来吧
Look at you. Haven't changed a bit.
妈 您真是一点都没变呢！
Oh my!
天啊！
Shuko, you're here!
秀子小姐来了啊？
Hey, Ryoko!
良子！
How've you been?
你过得好吗？
-Great! -THEY GET ALONG WELL.
-过得很好！ -（很要好）
UNCLE: SADAYOSHI
（叔父 定义）
FATHER: MASAYOSHI
（父亲 将贺）
PRESSURE
（低气压）
They get along well.
他们非常要好
What?
等等
Is that Shoko?
该不会是硝子吧？
You get prettier and prettier every time I see you.
天啊 长得越来越可爱了！
DOESN'T KNOW HOW TO REACT SO SHE NODS.
（不知该如何反应 古见同学只好点头）
Adorable.
好可爱
Oh yes, Shoko.
对了 硝子
Akira's here, so could you play with her?
晶在那边 陪她玩玩吧
COUSIN: AKIRA (JUNIOR HIGH YEAR 1)
（堂妹 晶 初一）
She hasn't seen you in so long.
那孩子很久没看到你了
She's feeling shy.
所以在害羞呢
KOMI IS GONE.
（古见同学不见了）
RUMBLE
（隆隆声）
STARTLE!!
（惊吓！）
DIDN'T MEAN TO STARTLE HER, AND STARTLED HERSELF MORE.
（没有打算吓人 古见同学自己反而更震惊）
AFRAID
（害怕）
DOESN'T WANT TO SCARE HER
（不想让她感到害怕）
JUMP
（吓到）
H-Hey, Shoko… Stop that!
等等 硝子姐姐 不要这样！
TICKLE TICKLE
（挠痒痒）
TWITCH
（抽搐）
The emotional distance between them has shrunk.
两人之间心灵的距离缩短了
WARMED UP TO KOMI
（变得愿意亲近她）
LIVING ROOM
（客厅）
GARDEN
（庭院）
Shoko.
硝子姐姐
TOILET
（厕所）
Um, Shoko?
我想问你一件事 硝子姐姐
Do you want to play a board game?
要不要来玩桌游？
NOD
（点头）
SUDDEN FLOOD OF TEARS
（突然大哭）
No, I'm alright.
我没事
I'm just so happy you want to hang out with me.
是因为你愿意理我 我太开心了
Until now you always just sat and looked at me.
直到去年 你都只会一言不发地看着我
-SHOSUKE, HOW HANDSOME! C'MERE! -KOMI WORKING ON FAMILY BONDING.
（笑介也变帅了 让我摸摸头吧 古见同学无法拿捏距离感）
-HOME EXPLODES. -CAT FINDS MONEY! GET 1 MILLION YEN.
（房子爆炸 养的猫捡到钱！获得一百万日元）
Three.
三
"You have an affair with your young boss. Get two million yen."
“和年轻社长发生婚外情 拿到两百万日元”
Shoko, go see your grandmother before dinner.
硝子 吃饭前记得去问候奶奶
In the Komi family,
在古见家
it is customary to keep Grandmother Komi, the head of the household,
照惯例要向一家之主的祖母
abreast of current going-ons and seek her wisdom.
报告最近的生活状况和烦恼
LOOKS LIKE GRANDMA SAID SOMETHING STERN.
（看似被祖母严厉训斥了一顿）
Come in.
进来吧
Sit.
坐下
Shoko, you're in high school now.
硝子已经是高中生了吧？
Are you having fun at school?
校园生活还愉快吗？
Is anything worrying or bothering you?
有没有什么感到担心的事 或是难过的事？
Have you made any friends?
有交到朋友吗？
Is that so! That's good.
这样啊 那就好
I'm happy for you.
真是太好了
By the way, have you met anyone special?
话说回来 有没有喜欢的男生啊？
What's that reaction?
你这是什么反应？
Show me your phone.
手机给我看一下
Who is this Hitohito Tadano?!
这个叫只野仁人的是谁？
I don't approve!
我可不会允许！
-Achoo! -Did you catch a cold?
-哈啾！ -哥哥 你在夏天还感冒啊？
MISSION 27 "IT'S JUST A FESTIVAL."
（任务27 去庙会）
Tadano! Let's meet at the festival tonight at six.
只野同学 今天的庙会 6点在现场集合
-Huh? Today? -Wear a yukata!
-什么？今天？ -记得穿浴衣来
See ya!
那就这样！
So I was told, and here I am.
虽说我听话穿上了
I feel like I stand out. Not many people are wearing yukata.
我这样会不会格格不入啊？ 没想到穿浴衣的人这么少
Whoa.
哇
-WORRIED THE YUKATA DOESN'T SUIT HER. -Oh, uh. I mean, you look really nice.
-（担心浴衣不适合自己） -不 非常适合你！
That just slipped out. Don't worry about it.
我只是一时说不出话来 完全不用担心啦！
Najimi… You could've said Komi was coming.
驯染那小子 都不跟我说古见同学也会来
LOOKS FOR HER NOTEBOOK.
（古见同学在找记事本）
FORGOT HER NOTEBOOK.
（忘了带记事本）
Forgot your pen and paper?
你忘了带纸吗？
Hey!
嗨！
Thanks for waiting, Tadano and Komi!
让你们久等了 只野同学、古见同学！
It's summer! Summer is here!
夏天到了呢 是夏天呢！
What's with the procession?
这队伍是怎么回事？
Huh? Oh, my plans for the festival were thousand-booked.
嗯？关于今天的夏季庙会 我不小心约了一千个人
Thousand-booked?
约了一千个人？
But a friend of a friend is still a friend, right?
不过朋友的朋友也都是朋友嘛
Let's go!
好了 出发吧！
What's with the mutant people skills?
这是什么惊人的社交能力啊？
Well, I guess we should go too.
总之我们也跟上去吧
What's wrong?
怎么了吗？
Ta… Ta…
只…
-Ta… -Hm?
-只… -什么？
Ta…
只…
This takes me back.
这感觉好令人怀念啊
Oh, anxious because you don't have your notebook?
我知道了 没带记事本让你没安全感？
It's alright. I'm here with you.
放心啦 有我在
Oh, uh, I don't mean it in a weird way.
不是 我没有其他意思
DECIDES NOT TO STRESS.
（决定去逛逛再说）
Hm? Wait a minute…
等等 现在这个状况…
Komi and I, alone at the festival.
和古见同学单独逛夏季庙会
-No, other people are here. Like Najimi! -BEST NOT TO THINK TOO DEEPLY.
-想太多了 还有驯染跟其他人啊！ -（决定不继续想 以免紧张）
Look, they're doing the Bon dance.
看 有人在跳盆舞呢
-Let's try target practice! -FLEES FROM AWKWARDNESS.
-要不要去玩打靶游戏？ -（觉得尴尬 顾左右而言他）
Huh? What's wrong with me today?
奇怪 我今天不太对劲啊
ANDORO CHOCOLATE
（阿多罗巧克力）
PRESSURE
（隆隆声）
I can't focus when I'm being watched.
看的我没办法专心
I mean, why am I being watched?
话说她为什么盯着我呢？
K-Komi, do you want to try?
古见同学 你要不要也来试试看？
Hey! So we meet again!
嗨 好久不见啊 各位！
It's Makeru Yadano.
我是矢田野真华留
Today I'm competing at target practice with Komi.
今天我要用打靶的方式 和古见同学一决胜负
Let's see who can get the most prizes! It's on, Komi!
看看谁击落的奖品比较多 我们来比赛 古见同学！
TARGET PRACTICE BEST OF FOUR
（打靶四局定胜负）
You lose!
你输了！
It's a tie.
我们平手
Miss, bring back the gun!
小姑娘 把枪还给我
Hey!
喂！
Komi! Tadano!
古见同学、只野同学！
Let's play Candy Cutout!
一起来玩切糖游戏吧！
In Candy Cutout,
所谓的“切糖游戏”
a toothpick is used to cut out a shape from a flat piece of candy.
就是要用牙签等道具 将片状糖块沿着图案轮廓取出来
Successful attempts may be exchanged for a prize.
如果能完整取出 就能换奖品
Oops.
唉唷
-HASN'T SUCCEEDED ONCE. -I'm kinda hooked. This is my 15th try.
-（一次都没成功） -我瘾上来了 这是第15块
You're a gambler in the making.
你真的很喜欢赌博类的刺激游戏呢
Ta… Ta… Ta-Ta-Ta… Ta-Ta-Ta…
只…
Ta… Ta… Y-Y-Y-Y…
只…你…
You're good at this, Komi!
古见同学 你好厉害！
Are you two hungry?
你们两个饿不饿？
You got bored, didn't you?
你玩腻了对吧？
I'll go buy something!
我去买些吃的过来
Komi has been acting weird all day.
今天古见同学感觉一直都怪怪的
I guess she's not having fun…
是玩得不开心吗？
I should ask.
我来问问她
-Ta… -Ko…
-只… -古…
Oh, uh, no, you f-first.
没事 你先说吧
Ta…
只…
Tadano…
只野同学…
you…
穿浴衣…
look…
也…
nice… too…
很好看
Look nice?
很好看？
Oh!
啊
LOOKS FOR HER NOTEBOOK
（古见同学在找记事本）
FORGOT HER NOTEBOOK
（忘了带记事本）
Forgot your pen and paper?
你忘了带纸吗？
Ta… Ta-Ta-Ta-Ta-Ta-Ta…
只…
Is that what you've been trying to say all this time?
你一直想说的就是这件事吗？
He cut out his candy really well.
他完整地沿着图案取出了糖
Look! Look, Tadano.
你看 只野同学
My tongue is blue!
蓝舌头
Yeah. Okay.
好啦
Komi!
古见同学！
Sorry for keeping you waiting!
对不起 让你等这么久！
-The usual crowd. -WASN'T WAITING.
-又是平时的那群人 -（根本没在等）
Ko…
古…
-Yuka…ta. -PROMPTLY FAINTED.
-浴衣… -（看到古见同学穿浴衣就昏倒了）
What's her deal?
这个人是怎么回事啊？
Next let's go play the rope lottery!
接下来我们去玩抽绳子游戏！
-Which should I pull? -I worry for Najimi's future…
-要抽哪个好呢？ -这家伙的未来还真令人担心
The rope lottery. Just pull a rope and get the attached prize.
所谓的“抽绳子游戏” 就是能获得绳子后面绑的奖品
It's a simple festival game.
是简单易懂的夜市摊贩游戏
I definitely want the top prize.
要抽当然就要抽到头奖
That rope is way older than the rest!
那绳子明显比其他绳子老旧！
It's the most ragged!
选这里面最破烂的绳子
This is it!
就是它！
POCKET TISSUE
（小包纸巾）
Tadano! Take out the enemy!
只野同学 你要替我报仇！
I'll pay you.
钱我来出！
Huh?
什么？
If I must.
真拿你没办法
Step right up.
谢谢惠顾
Which one should I pull?
该选哪根好呢？
Whoooooa!
啊！
Alright, this one.
那我选这根
POCKET TISSUE
（小包纸巾）
Granny, none of these are winners.
婆婆 该不会根本抽不到好奖品吧？
That's not true.
怎么可能
Komi, you're our last hope! Please!
古见同学 现在只能靠你了 拜托你了！
HAPPY TO BE RELIED UPON.
（被依赖很开心）
Yes.
是啊
Of course there are some winners.
怎么可能抽不中好奖品呢
This is a business after all.
我好歹也是在做生意啊
I've got to play fair.
堂堂正正经营才公平
But you know…
可是啊…
there are strategies, grasshopper!
做生意也是要 讲究对战方式啊 年轻人！
The old lady's vibe changed!
婆婆的气场改变了！
The rope attached to the PlayStore V!
首先是绑在 第五代游戏商店机上的绳子
It looks old and worn.
看起来很老旧
But that's a fake!
但那是障眼法
It's switched with a new rope partway.
在中间已经换成新的绳子了
And facial expressions.
再来是我的表情
People with no guts don't choose the ropes that I don't react to.
没有胆量的人根本不敢选 我面无表情时的那根绳子
Well, those are decoys anyway.
不过选那根绳子也是抽不中的
It's no use!
白费功夫！
Color, aroma, thickness… Many tricks.
此外在颜色、气味、粗细上 我也动了很多手脚
The more you think, the tighter the trap!
考虑得越多 就越可能中计
That's how it's done!
这游戏就是设计成这样！
ISN'T THINKING ABOUT ANYTHING.
（什么都没在想）
Yay!
好耶！
Komi looks beautiful no matter what she does.
古见同学无论在做什么 都美得像一幅画
Huh? Nakanaka?
什么？是中中同学？
Elegant red servants of the water.
在这流丽赤水中的仆人们
Come to your master.
快到我身边集合吧
She's muttering something.
她念念有词
Heh.
哼
Until we meet again.
后会有期
-KOMI DIDN'T NOTICE. -NAKANAKA GOT A PITY PRIZE.
（古见同学没注意到她 中中同学是安慰奖）
Komi!
古见同学！
I finally found you!
终于找到你了！
Stay where you are.
你站在那里 不要动哦
Could you squat down?
可以蹲下来吗？
Yes, like that.
很好 就是这个高度
I bought a frankfurter!
我帮你买了香肠
C'mon, eat my frankfurter!
请吃我的香肠
What's she doing to Komi?!
这个人想让古见同学做什么？
I'll eat it for you.
我来帮你吃吧
MUNCH MUNCH
（咀嚼）
Something fun's happening over there! Let's go!
那边好像很好玩 去瞧瞧！
GLASS ART
（玻璃工艺）
DEAD END!
（死定了！）
Komi!
古见同学
NEAR TEARS
（泫然欲泣）
Even if you get lost, you can just contact me on your phone.
就算走失了 可以用手机联络 别担心
OH YEAH!
（都没有想到）
I messaged Najimi, so let's wait here.
我联络了驯染 我们在这里等他吧
So many people.
人好多啊
Hm?
嗯？
YES
（是啊）
I guess you were happy to meet up with everyone.
能跟大家会合 很开心吧
IT WAS FUN WITH JUST THE TWO OF US AS WELL.
（和只野同学单独在一起的时候 我也很开心）
Huh?
什么？
SCRAPE
（擦掉）
YES
（是啊）
Hey!
喂！
Oh, Najimi and the gang are back.
驯染他们来了
Komi!
古见同学！
Look, my white chocolate banana.
你看 我的白巧克力香蕉棒
-Suck… -Don't say it!
-你舔… -不准再说下去了！
MISSION 28 "IT'S JUST THE END OF SUMMER."
（任务28 暑假要结束了）
Welcome, Komi!
欢迎你来 古见同学！
Come in! Don't mind the mess.
快进来吧 虽然家里很脏
Hey, this is my place.
喂 这可是我家
Uh, c'mon in.
请进
K-Komi is in my place…
古见同学在我家
Komi came over to Tadano's place?
古见同学在只野同学家？
I can't believe it.
这是不可能的
Something's here.
有人来了
Ta-da!
请看！
This is Tadano and his sister's room!
这里就是只野同学和他妹妹的房间！
Huh.
这样啊
Hitohito, are these your friends?
哥哥 你朋友来了啊？
Ah.
喔
Oh, hello.
各位好
Thanks for always being nice to my brother.
家兄总是承蒙各位的照顾
I'm his little sister, Hitomi Tadano.
我是他妹妹只野瞳
We share the room, so you'll see me around,
因为我们共享一个房间 如果我打扰到了各位
but pay me no mind.
还请多包涵
THEY'RE SOMEHOW EXCITED.
（感到兴奋）
Long time no see, Hitomi! It's been what, a year?
好久不见 瞳瞳 我们几年没见了啊？
Najimi! You've… changed?
驯染哥哥 等等 还是该叫驯染姐姐？
I'm Yamai. Thanks for having me.
我是山井 不好意思来打扰
You're welcome.
欢迎你
Wow, she's so beautiful.
是美女
Is she with my brother?
该不会在跟哥哥交往吧？
-Hey, Hitohito. -Huh?
-哥哥 你过来一下 -嗯？
What did you do?
你用了什么手段？
-What did you do?!
-什么？ -你用了什么手段？
Uh…
什么意思？
I have gathered you here today
今天找各位在此集合
in order to carry out an important mission.
是为了执行一项重要任务
To tell the truth…
其实…
I haven't finished a single bit of my summer homework.
我的暑假作业通通没做完呢
Ah, I had a feeling that was it.
嗯 早就猜到了
Yes! As I was saying.
好的 所以呢！
I must ask you to show me your homework!
我想抄你们的作业！
Why are you so okay with this?
这家伙为何反而是理直气壮的态度？
This happened last year too.
今年又是这样
No time management.
太不会规划时间了
-KOMI IS DUMBSTRUCK. -That's harsh.
-（不敢置信的眼神） -用不着这么夸张吧？
What is this?
怎样啦？
Let one who has finished their homework cast the first stone!
只有写完作业的人 才有资格对我扔石头！
Of course I'm done.
我当然写完了
Me too.
我也是
If I stay up all night, I'll fini--
我今晚熬夜就能写完…
So typical.
凡人
Tadano, you never let me down.
只野同学 你永远不会让我失望
Anyway, you should never copy homework.
话说回来 不可以抄别人的作业吧
Komi, you don't have to share your notes.
古见同学 你不用借他笔记本
Huh?!
什么？
Okay, we'll do our homework, but you guys can just relax.
那我们两个就来写作业 但古见同学 你们就没事做了
I'LL STUDY TOO.
（我也来复习作业）
Wow, great!
你真是了不起！
Alright, since I'm here,
那我也要利用这难得的机会
I'll just watch Komi.
好好欣赏古见同学
Summer's over for another year.
今年夏天也快结束了呢
That was fast.
时间过得真快
Yeah.
就是啊
We sure had fun!
玩得好过瘾啊
We didn't do anything for the first week, though.
虽然第一个礼拜什么都没做
First there was the pool.
我们先是去了游泳池
I went 51 times this year alone!
光是今年我就去了51次
Huh? Do we even have 51 days of vacation?
什么？怎么比暑假的天数还多啊？
Komi fell and scraped her knee.
古见同学还摔倒受伤
Is it better now?
膝盖的伤已经痊愈了吗？
When Komi fell, Yamai and the others filed down the spot on the ground.
后来山井他们还跑去锉平 当时害你摔伤的那个地板
I have a picture. Do you want to see?
我拍下了地板的照片 要看吗？
Really? Show me!
真的吗？我想看！
Here.
就是这个
Oh, I saw Komi at the library.
对了 我还在图书馆看到古见同学
Then later at the park too.
后来在公园也有看到
-YOU SHOULD'VE SAID HI. -Ah, you're right.
-（你应该打声招呼的） -对 你说得没错
I'll do that next time.
下次我会叫你的
We went to the festival too!
我们还去了夏季庙会
That reminds me, Tadano. What was your Candy Cutout prize?
对了 只野同学 玩切糖游戏得到的奖品呢？
Oh, I forgot to get it.
啊 我忘记去换奖品了
Huh? What a waste.
什么？好可惜！
Yamai, did you hang out with Komi?
山井有和古见同学一起出去玩吗？
Huh?
什么？
You said the two of you were going to do something.
你不是说要找她单独出去玩吗？
Oh, about that…
那是因为…
Oh, I see, you couldn't ask her out.
我懂了 原来你没邀请她呀
W-W-W-What's wrong, Komi?
你怎么了？古见同学！
SORRY. I'M FINE.
（对不起 我没事）
I
（我）
I NEVER WANTED SUMMER BREAK TO LAST LONGER BEFORE.
（我这是生平第一次 希望暑假不要结束）
TEARY-EYED…
（含泪）
Me too! I don't want it to end either!
我也是！我也不希望暑假结束！
I'll never finish my homework!
暑假作业写不完啦！
Okay, let's cut the chatter and get to it.
好啦 那就别再闲聊了 快来写作业吧
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻译：薛卓